Guide to the Todd-Bingham Picture Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- SMALL FOLIOS, Series IV; 12; folios
  - Amherst, Massachusetts and Environs
    - Amherst College
      - Williston Hall, North College, Chapel (Box 173)
    - Amherst, Massachusetts and other cities
      - Amherst, Massachusetts
        - "Convent": a school run by Mary E. Stearns, ca. 1892-1900 (Box 174)
        - Todd, David Peck
          - Home, 1887 (Box 174)
          - Observatory and observatory home, ca. 1903 (Box 174)
      - Other cities, 23 May 1896
        - Holyoke, Massachusetts: church interiors and city views (Box 174)
        - Northampton, Massachusetts: court house (Box 174)
        - Springfield, Massachusetts: from Arsenal Tower (Box 174)
        - South Deerfield, Massachusetts: Mount Sugarloaf (Box 174)
        - South Hadley, Massachusetts: from Mount Holyoke (Box 174)
        - Whately, Massachusetts: Whately Glen (Box 174)
  - Astronomy
    - U.S.S.R.: Bobinsky estate, 1914 (Box 175)
    - U.S.S.R.: Bobinsky estate, David Peck Todd visit, 1914 August 21
      - Arrival (Box 176)
      - Approach to house (Box 176)
      - Some of women mowers of lawn (Box 176)
      - Close-up of women mowers with David Peck Todd (Box 176)
      - David Peck Todd with instrument on porch and unidentified persons (Box 176)
      - David Peck Todd with instrument borrowed from Kiev Observatory (Box 176)
      - Only result of exposure to solar corona (Box 176)
      - David Peck Todd on porch beside telescope (Box 176)
    - South Africa: Capetown Observatory (Box 175)
  - Japan
    - Ainu people ca. 1896: color prints (professional) of Japanese life and people (Box 177)
    - Woodblock prints, drawings and memorabilia of Japanese art and life. (Box 178)
  - Todd Loomis Family Members
    - Portraits and sketches of David Peck Todd, Mabel Loomis Todd, and Eben Jenks Loomis, 1918, 1928, 1931, n.d. (Box 179)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Family friends
      - Campbell, Catharine (Box 180)
      - Curtis, Mrs. A.C.: "Masque of the Blue Garden," and Beacon Hill house, 1913,Aug 15. (Box 180)
      - Davis, Elmer 1955 Apr 24 (Box 180)
      - Ivanovski, Catharine (?) (Box 180)
      - James, Arthur Curtis (Box 180)
      - Lloyd, B. J. 1907 (Box 180)
      - Lukeman, Augustus: portrait and artwork 1913 Meyer, Agnes E. (Box 180)
      - Palmer, George Herbert: portrait and home 1920, n.d. (Box 180)
      - Wickerson, George W. 1902 Jun (Box 180)
      - Unidentified (Box 180)
    - New York and Washington, D.C.
      - New York
        - Ostego County, New York: birthplace of Eben Jenks Loomis (Box 181)
        - Watkins Glen, New York: Rainbow Falls, 1879 July (honeymoon site for DPT and MLT) (Box 181)
      - Washington, D.C.
        - "Delfthaven," Cleveland Park, Washington, D.C.: Eben Jenks Loomis' home, 5 Oct 1897 (Box 181)
    - Paintings
      - Loomis, Eben Jenks (1909?) (Box 182)
      - Shoemaker, W. L. (Box 182)
    - Prints, color
      - Bermuda 1905 (Box 183)
      - Columbia Expedition 1893 (Box 183)
      - Europe ca. 1900 (Box 183)
    - Sketches
      - Hilder, Howard: pencil drawings (Box 184)
- LARGE FOLIOS, Circa 1850s-1966; Series V
  - Millicent Todd Bingham
    - Amherst, Massachusetts, undated
      - Auction poster (Box 185)
      - Map (Box 185)
    - Certificates
      - Council of American Geographical Society, 1915 (Box 185)
      - Sociedad Geographica de Lima, 1921 (Box 185)
    - Hog Island, Maine
      - Map (Box 185)
      - Poster (Box 185)
    - Portraits, 1918, undated (Box 185)
    - Vassar College, 1902; 1907
      - Class photos (Box 185)
      - Glee Club (Box 185)
      - Calendar (Box 185)
  - David Peck Todd
    - Astronomical photographs, drawings, and charts, undated
      - Celestial charts, Litchfield Observatory (Box 186)
      - Hamilton College, by C.H.F. Peters (Box 186)
      - Eclipses, undated (Box 186)
      - Equipment, undated (Box 186)
      - Jupiter, first satellite of, undated (Box 186)
    - Certificates and diplomas
      - American Bibl Society, 1874 (Box 186)
      - Amherst College, 1875; 1878 (Box 186)
      - Astronomiche Gesellschaft, 1877 (Box 186)
    - New York Herald
      - Front-page model, 1925 January 25 (Box 186)
    - Portrait, undated
      - Pencil sketch by Betty Graves (Box 186)
  - Mabel Loomis Todd
    - Blueprints—Coconut Grove, Floxida, home, undated (Box 187)
    - Certificates
      - Daughters of the American Revolution, 1894; 1896 (Box 187)
      - George Washington Memorial Association, 1898 (Box 187)
    - Dickinson, Emily
      - Map of Massachusetts area for Richard Sewall's biography, undated (Box 187)
    - Posters—lectures on Mars, undated (Box 187)
    - Sketches—by Mabel Loomis Todd, undated (Box 187)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Europe
      - Art work, engravings, photographs (Box 188)
    - Freitas, John M.
      - Fairhaven, Massachusetts landsite (Box 188)
    - Howe, Thomas
      - Family tree, annotated by MTB(?) "Howe and Sayre's family tree. EJL." (Box 188)
    - Japan
      - Prints (Box 188)
    - Surveys
      - Fairhaven, Massachusetts(?) (Box 189)
    - C. W Sykes, "1400 Stats"
      - Charts and illustrations of the planets (Box 189)
- DAGUERREOTYPES, Series VI
  Conditions Governing Access
  Due to the physical nature of the material in series VI, staff supervision is required.
  - Dickinson, William Austin, 1856, undated (Box 190, Folder 1-2)
  - Loomis, [Collette?], undated (Box 190, Folder 3)
  - Loomis, [Collette?]and Eben Jenks, "Collins, Artist, Springfield" printed on label affixed to cover glass (Box 190, Folder 4)
  - Loomis, Eben Jenks, undated (Box 190, Folder 5)
  - Loomis, George, undated (Box 190, Folder 6)
  - Loomis, Nathan, "Pecks/Patent" and "April 30/1850" stamped on plate, "Prof. Nathan Loomis/About 1850" handwritten on card enclosed in box, Circa 1850 (Box 190, Folder 7)
  - Loomis, Nathan, "Cooley" and "Springfield" stamped on mat, in box with Waite Jenks Barber Loomis (Mrs. Nathan), undated (Box 190, Folder 8)
  - Loomis, Waite Jenks Barber Loomis, "Cooley" and "Springfield" stamped on mat, in box with Nathan Loomis, undated (Box 190, Folder 8a)
  - Todd, Rhoda Peck with unidentified child, ambrotype, undated (Box 190, Folder 9)
  - Wilder, Rev. John, "H.H. 40" stamped on corner of plate, undated (Box 190, Folder 10)
  - Loomis, Waite Jenks Barber, tintype, "A.P. Critchow & Co.,/Manufacturers of/Daguerreotype Cases./A.P.C. & Co.,/Are the Original Inventors of the/Composition for the Union Case,/(so called,)including all the various shades/of color and fineness of texture pecu-/liar to their manufacture and of the/Embracing Riveted Hinges, thus/securing them from breaking out/as do others that are inserted/with or without a metal brace./Hinge Batented Oct. 14, 1856." printed on paper behind plate "Waterbury Conn. No15" stamped on mat, undated (Box 190, Folder 11)
  - Unidentified woman, ambrotype, "Cooke & Emerson's Patent Applied For" and "Providence, R.I." stamped on mat, undated (Box 190, Folder 12)
  - Unidentified man (Box 190, Folder 13)
  - Unidentified man (Box 190, Folder 14)
  - Unidentified man, ambrotype, "A.M. McKenney/Photographer/122(?) /Middle St.?Portland, ME," stamped on card behind plate, undated (Box 190, Folder 15)
  - Loomis, Collette, ambrotype, "From the/Springfield/ Photographic Gallery,/No's 34, 35 & 36,/Goodrich Black,/Near the Depot./Pictures/Made in any weather single or/in groups, from Miniature to/Life Size,/ the manner not to be surpassed./The Cheapest and Best Pictures/in the City" printed on a card behind plate. "Dean & Emerson: Patent Applied for" and "Worcestester Mass. No. 11" stamped on edge of mat., undated (Box 191, Folder 16)
  - Loomis, George, "Boston/Picture Company,/Tyler & Co./Cor. Winter & Washington Streets,/500 Daguerreotypes Executed Daily/by a new/German Invention and Machinery,/at their/Extensive Sky-Light/Rooms." printed on card behind plate, undated (Box 191, Folder 17)
  - Loomis, George, "Boston/Picture Company…,", Circa 1850 (Box 191, Folder 18)
    See also: box 191, folder 17
  - Loomis, J.B., ambrotype, "Taken/April 1st. 1857,/ 10 o'clock A.M./By Spooner Bros./Springfield/Mass./ "Single glass picture"/not an ambrotype/J.B. Loomis." handwritten in ink on card and behind plate (Box 191, Folder 19)
  - Loomis, Mary Sears (later married James M. Bagg), "Boston/Picture Company…"(See item 17), undated (Box 191, Folder 20)
  - Loomis, Sarah Elizabeth Denham (Mrs. George[underline]) "Apr 7th 1855/Bartlett/Hartford/Conn/20 years old" handwritten in pencil on box behind plate (Box 191, Folder 21)
  - Stevens, Susan (later married John Augustus Wilder), photograph on porcelain, "Littlefield, Parsons & Co.,/Manufacturers of/Daguerreotype Cases./L.P. & Co., are the sole/Proprietors and only legal Manu-/facturers of Union Cases, with the/Embracing Riveted Hinge./Patented October 14, 1856, /and April 21, 1857," printed on paper behind plate, undated (Box 191, Folder 22)
  - Warner, M.W., ambrotype, undated (Box 191, Folder 23)
  - Wilder, Rev. John, miniature painting on ivory, undated (Box 191, Folder 24)
  - Wilder, M.W.F.J, undated (Box 191, Folder 25)
  - Wilder, M.W.F.J., undated (Box 191, Folder 26)
  - Wilder, [M.W.F.?], "Holmes, Booth & Haydens'/ Daguerreotype,/Photographic/and/Ambrotype Goods,/ Of every description." printed on paper behind plate, undated (Box 191, Folder 27)
  - Wilder, [M.W.F?], undated (Box 191, Folder 28)
  - Unidentified young woman, undated (Box 191, Folder 29)
  - Unidentified woman, undated (Box 191, Folder 30)
  - Unidentified woman, ambrotype, "Ambrotype/ by R. Adams" stamped on mat, undated (Box 191, Folder 31)
  - Loomis, George, paper photograph on glass with oil painting backing, undated (Box 191, Folder 32)
  - Loomis, Collette, ambrotype, "Collette Loomis/ (Sister-Geo.Loomis)/died April 1861/at 20 years" handwritten in ink on paper formerly glued to rear of plate, undated (Box 191, Folder 33)
  - [Loomis, daughter of George Loomis?], paper photograph on glass with oil painting backing, undated (Box 192, Folder 34)
  - [Wilder, John?], undated (Box 192, Folder 35)
  - Loomis, Sarah Elizabeth Denham (Mrs. George[underline]) paper photograph on glass with oil painting backing, undated (Box 192, Folder 36)
- PAINTINGS, [ca. 1837-1920]; Series VII; 3 linear feet (1 box 5, unboxed items)
  This series contains eight paintings. One portrait of Mabel Loomis Todd was done by Howard Hilder. All others are identified as or believed to be the works of Mabel Loomis Todd.
  - "Butternut Home," New York, 1837 (Box 193)
  - "Tripoli Eclipse,", 1905 (Box 193)
  - Unidentified 1887 (Box 193)
  - Unboxed items
    - "Mabel Loomis Todd at Matsuba" by Howard Hilder 32" x 40" (Box 194)
    - Millicent Todd Bingham (portrait) 20"x 30" (Box 195)
    - Flowers (mirror) 20" x 30" (Box 196)
    - Flowers 20" x 24" (Box 197)
    - Flowers 20" x 36" (Box 198)
    - Portrait of Mabel Loomis Todd by Letitia [illegible], 1899 (Box 199)